A Guide to the Thomson Mason Papers, 1804-1912
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Thomson Mason Papers 1804-1912
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
135
2 boxes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
William F. Smith, 2003.
Biographical/Historical Information
Thomson Francis Mason (1785 - 1838) was the grandson of George Mason IV of Gunston Hall and the son of Thomson Mason of Hollin Hall. He dedicated his life to public service for the town of Alexandria. Mason served on the Alexandria Common Council, was elected Mayor of Alexandria four times, served as Justice of the Peace three times, and was the first judge of the Criminal Court of the District of Columbia. He also practiced law and served as President of both the Alexandria Canal and Middle Turnpike Corporation.
Scope and Content
This collection contains numerous documents, either personal or business, of Thomson Mason. All correspondence is Mason's unless otherwise indicated. Other documents found are legal ones dealing with all phases of Mason's practice, both in and out of Virginia. Several items are from his period as Mayor of Alexandria and President of Middle Turnpike Corporation. Early documents deal with the buying and selling of slaves.
Arrangement
Arrangement is chronological by year.
Index Terms
Persons:
Mason, Thomson Francis, 1785-1838; Smoot, W.A.
Subjects:
Administration of estates; Coleman family; Cornnwell family; Farquhar family; Slavery--Virginia
Contents List
- Promissory Note, Robert Robertson to Robert and John Gray, 1 May 1804. (Box-folder 135:1)
- Bill of Complaint, Marine Insurance Association against James Wilson, 1806. (Box-folder 135:2)
- Frederick Tridle Estate Document, 1809. (Box-folder 135:3)
- Documents re: Sally Price and Henry Taylor, February 1809. (Box-folder 135:4)
- Promissory Note, Joseph Milligan to Robert Gray, 17 September 1811. (Box-folder 135:5)
- Merchandise Receipt, Rebeckah Griffith to John Hamilton, 1811. (Box-folder 135:6)
- Thornton Estate Suit, 1812. (Box-folder 135:7)
- Stock Share, Snickers Pike Turnpike Company, 1813. (Box-folder 135:8)
- Lawsuit, Churchman v. Price & Tucker, 14 December 1813. (Box-folder 135:9)
- Lawsuit, Upton Beall v. Washington Drane, 3 March 1814. (Box-folder 135:10)
- Miscellaneous Receipts, 1814. (Box-folder 135:11)
- Promissory Note, George Awman to Benjamin Price, 25 December 1814. (Box-folder 135:12)
- Receipt, T.F. Mason to Chas. Decton, 7 January 1815. (Box-folder 135:13)
- Promissory Notes, 1815. (Box-folder 135:14)
- Rental Agreement, Walter Brookes to Capt. Benjamin Price, 12 August 1815. (Box-folder 135:15)
- Document retaining T.F. Mason's Services, 15 August 1815. (Box-folder 135:16)
- Promissory Note, Thompson Violett to Robert Gray, 7 October 1815. (Box-folder 135:17)
- Slave Sale, William Lender to T.F. Mason, 20 December 1816. (Box-folder 135:18)
- Business Correspondence and Receipts, 1816. (Box-folder 135:19)
- Promissory Note, Jno. [?] to Robert Gray, 19 June 1816. (Box-folder 135:20)
- Business Correspondence and Receipts, 1817. (Box-folder 135:21)
- Correspondence, William Robinson retaining T.F. Mason to handle matter of runaway slave, 1818. (Box-folder 135:22)
- Receipts, 1818. (Box-folder 135:23)
- Business Correspondence, 1819. (Box-folder 135:24)
- Indenture, John Mason from Edgar Marty, 13 March 1819. (Box-folder 135:25)
- Bill for Merchandise, Presley Cordell to Sarah Price, 23 January 1819. (Box-folder 135:26)
- Indenture, Lawrence Simpson to Samuel Catts, 30 June 1820. (Box-folder 135:27)
- Indenture, William Miles to Thomson Mason,20 July 1820. (Box-folder 135:28)
- Chancery Court Suit, William Yeaton v. David Lenox,May 1820. (Box-folder 135:29)
- Correspondence and Receipts, 1820. (Box-folder 135:30)
- Promissory Note, Charles Farquhar to Lawrence Myers, 1820. (Box-folder 135:31)
- Business Correspondence, 1821. (Box-folder 135:32)
- Estate Accounting, John May Estate, 8 October 1821. (Box-folder 135:33)
- Business Correspondence, 1822. (Box-folder 135:34)
- Business Correspondence, 1823. (Box-folder 135:35)
- Business Correspondence, 1824. (Box-folder 135:36)
- Business Correspondence, 1825. (Box-folder 135:37)
- Estate Inventory, Constant Cornwell Estate, 12 December 1825. (Box-folder 135:38)
- Administrators Bond, Robert Lang for Estate of Robert Casey, 12 May 1826. (Box-folder 135:39)
- Estate Appraisal, Jesse Cornwell Estate - lists slaves. 20 May 1826. (Box-folder 135:40)
- Business Correspondence, 1826. (Box-folder 135:41)
- Business Correspondence, 1827. (Box-folder 135:42)
- Correspondence, Personal, Mayoral, Legal. 1828. (Box-folder 135:43)
- Ledger (part of), Middle Turnpike Road Construction, 1829. (Box-folder 135:44)
- Mayoral Correspondence, 1829. (Box-folder 135:45)
- Business Correspondence, 1829. (Box-folder 135:46)
- Personal Correspondence, 1829. (Box-folder 135:47)
- Business Correspondence, 1830. (Box-folder 135:48)
- Indenture, William McCarty to George Mason, 1 October 1830. (Box-folder 135:49)
- Receipt for Merchandise, William Fowle from Charles Farquhar, 10 December 1830. (Box-folder 135:50)
- Business Correspondence, 1831. (Box-folder 135A:1)
- Bill for Services/Goods, Horatio Day (shoemaker) to Charles Farquhar, June-December 1832. (Box-folder 135A:2)
- Business Correspondence, 1832. (Box-folder 135A:3)
- Insurance Policy, Fire Insurance Company of America, 25 February 1833. (Box-folder 135A:4)
- Deed, 604 King Street, Elizabeth Coleman to Charles Farquhar. 13 May 1833. (Box-folder 135A:5)
- Business Correspondence, 1833. (Box-folder 135A:6)
- Indenture, Thomas and Margaret Coleman to Charles Farquhar, 1 March 1833. (Box-folder 135A:7)
- Bills/Receipts, Charles Farquhar, 1833. (Box-folder 135A:8)
- Business Correspondence, 1834. (Box-folder 135A:9)
- Literature Lottery Drawing - Wilmington, Delaware, 28 August 1834. (Box-folder 135A:10)
- Receipts, Charles Farquhar, 1834. (Box-folder 135A:11)
- Accounting for Services, Charles Farquhar to George Swaine, 1834. (Box-folder 135A:12)
- Promissory Note, Charles Farquhar to George Swaine, 1835. (Box-folder 135A:13)
- Receipts, Charles Farquhar, 1835. (Box-folder 135A:14)
- Business Correspondence, 1835. (Box-folder 135A:15)
- Receipts, Charles Farquhar, 1836. (Box-folder 135A:16)
- Promissory Notes, 1836. (Box-folder 135A:17)
- Business Correspondence, 1836. (Box-folder 135A:18)
- Receipts, Charles Farquhar, 1837. (Box-folder 135A:19)
- Promissory Note, Charles Farquhar, 1837. (Box-folder 135A:20)
- Judgement for suit against Jesse Cornwell estate, 1837. (Box-folder 135A:21)
- Business Correspondence, 1837. (Box-folder 135A:22)
- Business Correspondence, 1838. (Box-folder 135A:23)
- Business Correspondence, 1842. (Box-folder 135A:24)
- Bills of Lading, Hilles, Boyd & Company, 1868. (Box-folder 135A:25)
- Bills of Lading, Smoot & Company, 1870. (Box-folder 135A:26)
- Checks written by William Smoot, 1882. (Box-folder 135A:27)
- Business Correspondence, William Smoot & Company, 1891. (Box-folder 135A:28)
- Business Correspondence, William Smoot & Company, 1901. (Box-folder 135A:29)
- Personal Correspondence, William A. Smoot, 1901. (Box-folder 135A:30)
- Letter from L.E. Smoot to father, 1910. (Box-folder 135A:31)
- Letter from C.C. Randolph to brother, 1912. (Box-folder 135A:32)
- Miscellaneous Documents, not dated. (Box-folder 135A:33)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, not dated. (Box-folder 135A:34)
- Alexandria Gazette, 30 May 1862. (Box-folder 135A:35)
- Alexandria Gazette, 12 July 1864. (Box-folder 135A:36)